<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certayne short questions and answeres Very profitable and necessarye for yong children, and such as are desirous to be instructed in the principles of the Christian fayth.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841406</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841406</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5987</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5987)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 561:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certayne short questions and answeres Very profitable and necessarye for yong children, and such as are desirous to be instructed in the principles of the Christian fayth.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Middleton, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:1"/>
            <p>Certayne ſhort Queſtions and <hi>Anſweres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Very profitable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye for yong Children, and
ſuch as are deſirous to be inſtructed in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fayth. (⸫)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by Henry Middleton, <hi>for Thomas
Man.</hi> 1580.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:2"/>
            <head>Certayne ſhort Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Anſweres, very profitable
and neceſſarie for yong Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſuch as are deſirous to be
inſtructed in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Chriſtian Fayth.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is GOD?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> A Spirite.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Why doeſt thou not ſaye
he is Almighty, Eternal, Omnipotent, Inuiſible, conteyning all, and not
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> All this I do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe.
But I anſwere ſimply as Chriſt ſayth: <hi>Iohn 4. The ſubſtance of
God is Spiritual, and not Carnall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> How is Man then ſayde to be
the Image of God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is ſpoken of the
prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall part of Man, which is his Soule, whiche the Apoſtle ſayeth is
created in the true likeneſſe of God, in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and
holyneſſe: ſo is it like God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb facs="tcp:5987:3"/>both
immortall and ſpirituall a God is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Then is the Soule of man of
one nature and ſubſtaunce with God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> No, it is a ſubſtance
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, created of God, infuſed into ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and it is immortall.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> How is God to be
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> In Spirit and Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> How in Spirite?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> With a deuoute minde, a
faithfull heart, in a ſpirituall manner, not with earthly affection.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Howe then muſt hée
bée worſhipped in Truth?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> That is, according to hys holy
will in his Word, not according to mans fantaſie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Howe if in worſhipping of
God we be not myndfull of hym in our Prayers?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> Then it is vayne (ſayeth
Chriſt) to worſhip him with our lippes and oure heartes farre from hym, and
withoute we pray in Spirite, Prayer <pb facs="tcp:5987:3"/>preuayles
not, neyther dothe it pearce the eares of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Then a faithful &amp; deuout
mind is ſpecially required in prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It is ſo, which God for
Chriſtes ſake graunt vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> What is Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> Perfecte God, and perfecte
man.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Howe doeſt thou knowe he is
God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Bycauſe he is equall wyth hys
father.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Howe knoweſt thou he is
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with his father?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Bycauſe he ſayth, <hi>I and
the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are one,</hi> alſo <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth, <hi>He being equall
with his Father, tooke vpon hym the ſhape of a ſeruant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> How doeſt thou know that he is
man?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Bycauſe he tooke naturall
fleſhe of the virgin Mary, and was concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the holy Ghoſt withoute
ſinne, and in that naturall body dyed a moſt paynefull deathe to
redéeme vs from our ſynnes (as the Apoſtle ſayeth:)
<pb facs="tcp:5987:4"/>
               <hi>He came into the world to ſaue
ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> What is the Catholique
Church?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is a congregation of all
faithfull men, diſperſed throughout the whole world, amongſt whome the
pure word of God is preached, and the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are miniſtred, according
to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Art thou the child of
God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> I am.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> By Nature, or by Grace?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> Not by Nature, for ſo we are
the children of Gods wrath.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Now knoweſt thou that thou art
the child of God by Grace?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Bycauſe he hath giuen the
ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of his ſpirit into our hearts, which crieth <hi>Abba Pater,</hi>
whiche ſpirite wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth to oure ſpirite, that we are the ſonnes of
God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Is not this preſumption for
a ſinner to ſay he is Gods ſonne?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It is no preſumption ſo to
ſay, ſo it be holye preſumption to call oure ſelues Gods children, from
the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, ſeing Chriſt hath
<pb facs="tcp:5987:4"/>willed vs in prayer to call his
Father our Father.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Of what ſubſtance is the
holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> A Spirituall ſubſtance as
God is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Of what Nature?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> Being God, one of nature with
God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Then the holy Ghoſt is
God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> He is ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there be thrée
Gods, as God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> No, the diſtinction is in
perſon, not in deitie, as the Catholique fayth teacheth vs. The concluſion
ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is, that God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Father is our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Chriſt in his perſon is
our Redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the holy Ghoſt who procéedes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, is oure
ſanctifyer, and procéedes from them, euen as lighte and heate from the
Sonne, and yet ſo lightneth the whole Worlde, that it remayneth ſtill with
God, and is very God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> What is a Sacramente?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:5"/>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is a viſible ſigne of
an inuiſible grace, as for example, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherewith the childe is
baptiſed, is the viſible ſigne of the inuiſible grace of God, by
whoſe grace theſe our ſinnes be cleanſed by Chriſtes bloud, ſo
likewiſe the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal Bred &amp; Wine do ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of
Ieſus Chriſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally and truly, his body broken, &amp; his bloud ſhed
vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe for our ſalutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> According to this
defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Sacramentes be infinite. Let me knowe why Baptiſme and the
Lordes Supper are only alowed Sacramentes in the Church?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> Bycauſe they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by Gods worde, &amp; haue promiſes of grace and ſaluation annexed vnto
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Do Sacraments of
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues conferre grace?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> No, but God doth by them
exhibit graces vnto vs, for <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayeth, <hi>We Baptiſe with
Water, we miniſter the outwarde ſignes, but it is Chriſt whiche doth
Baptiſe with the holy Ghoſt:</hi> and by the outward Elementes by vs
mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred we do confirme the inward grace <pb facs="tcp:5987:5"/>which
is giuen by God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> What be thoſe graces that be
conferred from God to vs by theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Regeneration of life, increaſe
of ſpirituall bleſſings, forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and life
euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Then of neceſſitie all are
not ſaued which participate Baptiſme and the Lords Supper?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> So many are ſaued as are
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the inuiſible graces, whereof the Sacraments are viſible
ſignes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> How if a child borne of
belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing parents, be preuented with death before Baptiſme, and ſo
receyue not the viſible ſigne?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is moſt requiſite that
we endeuour to offer them to publique Baptiſme by all meanes lawful,
other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if we be hindered by ſome neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie not to be ſhunned,
yet we oughte to perſwade our ſelues that they are ſaued by the
inuiſible grace, bycauſe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of faithfull beléeuing
parents, are receiued in the couenaunt, and may be ſanctifyed in their
mothers wombes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:6"/>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Then what néedeth
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is of great neceſſitie
for the commaundements ſake, conteyned in the eight and twentieth of Mathew:
and to refuſe it, is to deſpiſe the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, for although he
worke ſometime without all meanes, yet muſt not we ceaſſe to vſe the
meanes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, when we are in a Chriſtian Church, and may haue them, that
is, to Baptiſe the whole World in the name of the Father, of the Sonne, and
of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Haue you no further rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
for the vſe of Baptiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> That is ſaid, is
ſufficient: yet I doe ſay further, it is the pledge of Gods couenant made
with vs, and the viſible ſigne of oure adoption that wée are his by
Grace and Faith in Chriſt, and the viſible marke, whereby wée are
knowen from the vncircumciſed ſort.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> What is Faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is a ſure truſt in God,
and in Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, and a <pb facs="tcp:5987:6"/>certaintie
of things promiſed by God, whiche can not otherwiſe be diſcerned, than
with the eye of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Whence commeth Faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is the gifte of God, as
Paule ſayth in the ſecond to the Epheſ. <hi>By grace you are ſaued
through Fayth, not of our ſelues, it is the gift of GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Doth Faith only iuſtifie a
man?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It doth Iuſtifie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> How is a iuſtifying faith
knowen from a dead fayth?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> By the fruites &amp; works
which are with faith that iuſtifieth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> What is Faith withoute good
life?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is dead.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> What are workes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> They be ſinne, be they
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo glorious before men.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> How come men by faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> In the tenth to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes
it is ſhewed, that <hi>Faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by hearing the Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Can a man be ſaued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:5987:7"/>faith in Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> No, for Chriſt ſaith,
<hi>Hee that beleeueth not, is conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned already.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="summary" type="catechism">
            <head>Theſe Queſtions are briefely collected out of the former,
for the help of ſuch as in a ſhorte ſumme are deſirous to learne by
hearte the chiefe principles of Chriſtian Religion.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label>
            </p>
            <p>God is a Spirite.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> How muſt he be
woorſhipped?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> In Spirite and truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> What is Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Chriſt is perfect God and
perfect Man.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> How know you he is God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Bycauſe he is equall with hys
Father.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> How know you he is Man?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Bycauſe in our nature he
redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs from our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> What is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholike
Church?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> All faythfull people diſperſed
throughout the whole world.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Art thou the ſonne of God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> I am.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:7"/>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Art thou the ſonne of God by
nature, or by grace?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> By grace.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Howe doeſt thou knowe that
thou art the ſonne of God by grace?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> The ſpirit doth witneſſe to
our ſpirit that we are the ſonnes of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Of what ſubſtance is the
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> A ſpirituall ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Of what nature?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> Of one with God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Then the holy ghoſt is
God?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> He is ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Then there be thrée Gods,
as God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> No, the diſtinction is in
perſons, not in deytie, as the Catholike Fayth teacheth vs. The concluſion,
then God the Father is our creator, Chriſt in his perſon oure
Redéemer, the holy Ghoſt who procedeth from both our ſanctifier, and
procéedes from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as light &amp; heate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonne, and ſo
lightneth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole world, and remayneth ſtill in God, and is very God.
<hi>Qu.</hi> What is a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:8"/>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> It is a viſible ſigne of
an inuiſible grace, as for example, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherewith the childe is
baptiſed, is the viſible ſigne of the inuiſible grace of God, by
whoſe grace theſe our ſinnes he cleanſed by Chriſtes bloud: ſo
lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſacramentall bread and wine do ſignifye to vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of
Ieſus Chriſt naturally and truly, both his body bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and his bloud
ſhed vpon the croſſe for our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> Do not theſe Sacraments of
themſelues conferre grace?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwere.</label> No, we (ſaith <hi>S.
Iohn</hi>) Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe with water, we miniſter the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſignes, but it
is Chriſte whiche doth Baptiſe with the holy Ghoſt, and by the outward
Elements by vs mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred we do confirme the inward grace, which is giuen by
God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Then of neceſſitie al are
ſaued whiche participate Baptiſme and the Lords Supper?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> So many are ſaued as are
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the inuiſible graces, whereof the ſacraments are viſible
ſignes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> How if a childe borne of
belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <pb facs="tcp:5987:8"/>parents be
preuented with deathe before Baptiſme, and ſo receiue not the viſible
ſigne?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It is moſt requiſite that we
doe preſerue it to publike Baptiſme by all meanes lawful, if not, yet they
be ſaued by inuiſible grace, bycauſe the children of faithfull
beléeuing parents are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifyed in their mothers wombes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Then what néede
Baptiſme?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It is of greate neceſſitie for
the commandements ſake, <hi>Math. 28.</hi> and to refuſe it, is to
deſpiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, for although he worke ſometime wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all
meanes, yet we muſt not ceaſſe to vſe the meanes appoynted, that is, to
baptiſe the whole world in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holy
ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> What is Faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It is a ſure truſt in God, and
Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Whence commeth Faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It is the gift of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Doth Faith only iuſtifie a
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It doth iuſtifie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Howe is a iuſtifying Fayth
knowen from a dead Fayth?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:9"/>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> By the fruites &amp; works which
are with faith that iuſtifyeth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> What is faith without good
life?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> It is dead.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> What are workes without
faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> They be ſinne, be they neuer
ſo gorgeous before men.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> How come men by faith?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> In the tenth to the Romaines,
<hi>Faith commeth by hearing the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> Can a man be ſaued without
Faith in Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſ.</label> No, for Chriſt ſayeth, <hi>He
that beleeueth not, is condemned already.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5987:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
